Hi, welcome back to Arya Nagarjuna.
And we are still in the
middle of this tough,
it became a tough chapter, right?
A chapter about investigating karma.
And we thought that we were going
to have a normal discussion, but
it's already gone off
on some difficult parts.
And by the way, now Nagarjuna,
having given the Abhidharma version of,
what do we call it, don't lose it?
- [Student] Don't go away.
- Don't go aways.
He's going, now he is going to give
a more standard Madhyamika discussion.
Here we go.
The next verse says,
,GAL TE LAS LA RANG BZHIN YOD,
,RTAG PAR 'GYUR BAR THE TSOM MED,
,LAS NI BYAS PA MA YIN 'GYUR,
,RTAG LA BYA BA MED PHYIR RO,
GAL TE LAS LA RANG BZHIN YOD
And karma, the laws of karma,
are something that you
and me feel instinctively.
We just talked, we had a discussion here
about it with our friends.
It feels like they are self-existent.
It feels like those laws are unbreakable,
cannot be changed,
and they come from their own side.
Like, I understand that in general
things are coming from me.
But who made the laws of the universe?
Who made the laws of karma?
And so Nargarjuna is going
to try to convince us
that our karma made the laws of karma.
And that just because laws of
karma are coming from karma,
doesn't mean they could work differently
then the way they do.
Just because something is empty,
doesn't mean that it will come
in a thousand different forms.
All right, GAL TE LAS LA RANG BZHIN YOD
If karma itself, if the laws
of karma had their own nature,
RTAG PAR 'GYUR BAR THE TSOM MED
there's no doubt that it
would be unchanging -- RTAG PA
If karma were coming from its own side,
it would never vary.
It would always stay the same.
It would be unchanging.
LAS NI BYAS PA MA YIN 'GYUR
If something is unchanging,
it cannot have involved an agent.
If karma, if anything in the universe
is unchanging, that means nobody did it.
Because if somebody did
it, then it would change
because the effects of doing
something get less over time.
Things fall apart.
That famous book title
"Things Fall Apart",
that's the nature of things.
So if things are created, they fall apart.
If things don't fall apart,
then they can not have had
someone create them.
Got it? That's all right, right?
LAS NI BYAS PA MA YIN 'GYUR
And RTAG LA BYA BA MED PHYIR RO.
If something is unchanging,
there cannot have been a process
of creation at the beginning of it.
Because the process of creation,
the process of pushing
something into being,
that energy which pushes the thing
into being is lost over time.
So if it's unchanging,
if karma has a nature of
its own, from its own side,
it's unchanging.
If it's unchanging, it cannot have had
the person who committed the karma.
No one made the karma.
Got it?
All right.
And I think of it as a driverless car.
And that used to be a
real serious argument,
but now we do have driverless cars.
So I want to say a driverless
car without a program.
A car driving itself without the internet.
How is that? For now.
I don't know what's coming later.
Next verse.
,CI STE LAS NI MA BYAS NA,
,MA BYAS PA DANG PHRAD 'JIGS 'GYUR,
,TSANGS SPYOD GNAS PA MA YIN PA'ANG,
,DE LA SKYON DU THAL BAR 'GYUR,
This is a tough verse,
although the words are not so difficult.
CI STE LAS NI MA BYAS NA
If you could have karma
without anyone doing it
because you say karma has
to have its own nature
which implies that karma never changes,
which means that it didn't have
anyone that did it. Got it?
So if you say karma has a nature,
then natures don't change.
Then okay, so someone, it cannot be anyone
who committed the karma
if it's unchanging.
Got it?
MA BYAS PA DANG PHRAD 'JIGS 'GYUR
Then you get into the problem of...
things could happen to you
without committing the karma before.
Let's go through the logic again.
He says, "Karma is self-existent",
meaning karma has its own nature.
Okay.
Nature, which we already
talked about in the chapter
"Investigation of Nature", or identity.
It means that it doesn't change.
Peripheral qualities change.
The color of the fire changes.
The fact that it's hot doesn't change.
That's self-nature. That's an identity.
It doesn't change.
So if something doesn't change,
if karma has a self-identity,
it cannot change.
No more than fire could become cold
and still be fire.
So therefore, no one did karma.
Therefore, you can have karmic
results without someone doing them.
Therefore, things can happen
to you that you don't deserve.
Got it? You okay? You following?
If karma's unchanging,
then nobody did karma.
But karma still works, so karma can work
without anybody doing it.
Therefore, things can happen
to you that you didn't deserve
because you didn't do anything.
Got it?
Then that's going to be a weird world.
MA BYAS PA DANG PHRAD 'JIGS 'GYUR
MA BYAS PA is the third law of karma.
If you don't do it, you
cannot get a result.
And he says, "No, now you have to
change the third law of karma."
If karma is self-existent,
then you could have karma running around
that no one committed.
Karmic results could happen to you
for things you never did.
Which is what you accuse the universe
constantly already. [laughter]
MA BYAS PA DANG PHRAD 'JIGS 'GYUR,
This 'JIGS is spelled with an S.
So it doesn't mean destroy,
it means, like 'JIGS MED.
You'd have to walk
around on eggshells. Why?
Things could happen to you
that you don't deserve.
Then you should be nervous.
In a world, where you
don't have to make karma
to get karma back, then
you better be careful.
You better keep your eyes out.
TSANGS SPYOD GNAS PA MA YIN PA'ANG
This is a weird example,
and maybe you got to think about
why he chose this example.
He says, "You could be a person
who keeps sexual purity very well,
and still you would have bad results."
Like the karmic results
of sexual impurity,
one of them is air pollution, for example.
So he says, "If you
could get karmic results
for things you never did,
then you could be a good monk,
and keep your morality, as far as sex,
and then still you would
live in a polluted country."
Okay?
You could get undeserved
karmic results.
MA YIN PA'ANG, DE LA
SKYON DU THAL BAR 'GYUR
These are all the examples
of problems that would come
from your idea that karma
has its own identity
in the same way that you thought
fire had it's own identity.
Okay? Cool.
All right.
I have a picture of... that was
supposed to be air pollution
without cars, or something.
I don't know.
Pretend there is no cars.
But it's still polluted.
You got the results of sexual misconduct,
even though you were very
pure with your behavior.
All right.
Why he chose that one out of the ten.
Maybe we all have this problem.
Maybe we all have some kind of problem.
All right, next verse.
,THA SNYAD THAMS CAD NYID DANG YANG,
,'GAL BAR 'GYUR BAR THE TSOM MED,
THA SNYAD THAMS CAD
THA SNYAD means expression,
and Choney Lama says,
"He's talking about how the world talks.
So sometimes in Buddhist books,
they will say, "Oh, come on look,
even in normal conversation
people don't accept that."
Even normal people in the
world wouldn't say that.
So that here it's THA
SNYAD THAMS CAD NYID DANG
Even when people get together and talk,
who are not Buddhist, they weren't
trained, still 'GAL BAR 'GYUR,
it would be a contradiction.
For example, here is the picture. Yay!
It would be a contradiction
to have a field
full of lettuce, I
guess, my enemy, lettuce,
and there is nobody who planted it.
You know?
So even with a good result,
like suddenly 2,000 heads of lettuce
grew in your garden by themselves,
still people would talk.
- What happened?
- I don't know. It just showed up.
- Wow, that's weird.
See, even people in the normal world
understand that it's weird to get a result
when you didn't do anything.
Like, I don't know,
suddenly your backyard
blooms with all kind
of delicious vegetables,
if there were such a thing.
BRTAG PA MTHA' BZUNG GI RIGS
PA, in theoretical case.
Then even in the normal world,
people would say something's
weird is going on.
He didn't plant any vegetables,
and look, he got all these
vegetables. 'GAL BAR 'GYUR
,BSOD NAMS DANG NI SDIG BYED PA'I,
,RNAM PAR DBYE BA'ANG 'THAD MI 'GYUR,
If you could get suddenly karmic results
without having done anything
because karma has its own nature,
then there would be no good
deeds and bad deeds, either.
You can forget the distinction.
You can forget the division
between good deeds and bad deeds
because you just going to get
randomly whatever you get.
So why talk about good
deeds and bad deeds?
Good deeds and bad deeds,
morality in Buddhism is defined
by the karma that you get back.
Okay?
How do you decide right and wrong
in a Buddhist world?
Does it hurt when it comes back,
or does it make you
happy when it comes back?
That's right or wrong.
That's the definition of right and wrong.
It's not even that it hurts someone else.
Ultimately, Buddhist
morality is based upon
will it hurt you if you do it?
And will it hurt you, will
it help you when you do it?
Okay?
By the way, always through
hurting someone else, right?
All right, next one.
Next verse.
,DE NI RNAM SMIN SMIN 'GYUR PA,
By the way,
I disagree with
this line in Choney Lama.
I think someone added it.
The Tengyur says different.
And Choney Lama's commentary says,
"matches the Tengyur."
So I think someone added
the root text later,
and was adding a different version.
It matters, okay?
So I am going to change
this line to fit the Tengyur
because that matches Choney Lama.
So here it is,
,DE NI RNAM SMIN SMIN 'GYUR PA,
,YANG DANG YANG DU RNAM SMIN 'GYUR,
If karma could come back
to you when you didn't
do anything in the first place,
then when karma ripens on you,
that ripening could ripen again.
If you could get a flat tire on your car
without hurting someone else's car,
then the flat tire would go flat, also.
[laughing]
The karma would pile up on itself.
If no one had to commit the
karma for you to get the result,
then you could keep getting results.
Not just one, but they
could repeat themselves.
,GAL TE RANG BZHIN YOD NA NI,
,GANG PHYIR LAS GNAS DE YI PHYIR,
Okay?
And then another problem.
And he kind of switches,
he's been talking about the result,
but now he talks about the karma itself.
If karma could come back to
you without doing anything,
then when you did do something,
that actually could go on forever,
and never produce a result.
If karma came from its own side,
then when you did something,
it would be logical that that
action would continue forever.
And it would never ripen
because the karma had its own
nature that doesn't change.
Identity doesn't change.
If the karma has an identity,
the definition of an identity
is that it doesn't change.
It stays with you.
So therefore, if karma is action,
then you would always
be in a state of action,
and you would never get
a result from the karma.
Then there would be no time
for the karma to come back
because you have to be
doing it all the time,
because it's not supposed to change,
because it has its own identity.
And you do not change identity.
Identity means something you
keep that doesn't change,
like heat with fire.
I have a nice picture.
I call this "Workaholic Karma".
And I think it would be
a nice name for a band.
"Workaholic Karma".
It means the karma keeps
working, and nothing happens.
[laughing]
You keep killing people,
or you keep saving life,
or donating to Club de Oro,
and it never comes back to you.
You just keep doing
it, doing it, doing it.
Because why?
Because karma can't change.
- Why? - It has an identity of its own.
- Why?
- Because it's not coming from me.
The laws of karma are not coming from me.
All right.
"Workaholic Karma"
I think it's going to
be a good book title.
Next verse.
,LAS 'DI NYON MONGS DAG NYID LA,
,NYON MONGS DE DAG YANG DAG MIN,
,GAL TE NYON MONGS YANG DAG MIN,
,LAS NI YANG DAG JI LTAR YIN,
The suffering of life,
the truth of suffering,
the first of the four higher truths,
arya truths, is suffering.
What's a second higher truth?
- [Student] Cause. - Is the cause.
Which is traditionally
divided into two, for $100.
The cause of all
suffering is traditionally
divided into two when you
teach the four truths.
- [Student] Misunderstanding.
- No.
- Cancel the bet.
LAS 'DI NYON MONGS.
LAS
- [Student] Karma and emotion.
- Karma and negative emotions.
You can call it mental afflictions,
but that word hasn't been
used since the late 1700s,
and Buddhist scholars.
Okay.
So anyway, let's call
it negative emotions.
LAS 'DI NYON MONGS
These are the two sources of suffering.
Here he says,
LAS 'DI NYON MONGS DAG NYID LA
Dirty karma,
that the essence of dirty karma
is negative emotions, isn't it?
Dirty karmas, dirty
karma, ZAG BCAS KYI LAS.
The nature of dirty karma is that
it is driven by your negative emotions.
NYON MONGS DE DAG YANG DAG MIN
Those negative emotions are not
YANG DAG, for $50.
YANG DAG
- Huh? - [Student] Pure.
- Yay! 50 dollars, give, by the way,
somebody won a 100 dollars
while you were gone.
Okay.
Pure. $100 for who can explain pure to me.
He says here,
"Your negative emotions are not pure."
[someone talking indistinctly]
I mean, does Nagarjuna,
does Arya Nagarjuna
really have to tell you
that your jealousy and anger are not nice.
Is that what he's doing?
Would he bother to tell you that?
- [Student] Pain and [unclear].
- Yay! $100 for Rebecca.
This pure means exists
from their own side.
Because obviously,
Nagarjuna is going to say,
"Hey, guess what? Your
jealousy is a bad thing."
- Wow, I didn't know.
[laughing]
So it's not pure.
GAL TE NYON MONGS YANG DAG MIN
If your negative emotions are impure,
then how can karma be pure?
- [Student] It can't.
- Because your negative
emotions drive your..
- [Student] Actions.
- Karma.
If the negative emotions are not pure,
meaning not coming from their own side,
then what they drive can be...
coming from its own side.
Got it?
And that's the last
verse, he just finished.
If they were unchanging, they'd be coming,
if they were coming from their own
side, they would be unchanging.
If they're unchanging,
you could get results
that you don't deserve.
Got it?
Therefore, I could prove
it to you another way.
- Look, karma doesn't
exist for its own side.
- Why?
It's made by things that don't
exist from their own side.
Got it?
If something makes another thing,
and it doesn't come from its own side,
then the thing that the thing makes
shouldn't come from its own side, either.
Got it?
Therefore, karma doesn't
come from its own side.
I just proved it to you a different way.
I have an apple rotten, apple rotten,
rotten apple.
I was thinking of Johnny Rotten Pizza.
Ha-ha.
Anyway,
if the apple's rotten, then the apple pie
you make from the apple is going to be...
- [Student] Rotten.
- Rotten.
Why am I talking about that?
- [Student] Then karma...
- What's the rotten apple?
- [Student] Negative emotions.
- Negative emotions.
- What's the pie?
- [Student] Karma.
- Karma, good.
If you use rotten apples
to make an apple pie,
then the apple pie is
going to taste rotten.
If you use
un-self-existent jealousy to create karma,
then the karma that's made from
the un-self-existent jealousy
is going to be un-self-existent.
Rotten and rotten, got it?
All right, just for fun,
we're going to do a Sanskrit
word called kleśa (klesha).
And I don't know, it's
a big theme right here.
Negative emotions.
So most of you know this word already.
But I had to put something.
Klesha means a negative emotion.
It comes from the word √kliś
which means to be bothered,
or irritated, or distressed.
And the English cognate is
"holly" because it's prickly.
So when you talk about negative emotions
in Buddhism, RANG RGYUD LDAN
GYI GANG ZAG GI SHES RGYUD
MA ZHI BAR BYED PA'I SEMS BYUNG SEMS PA
Say RANG RGYUD LDAN GYI
GANG ZAG GI SHES RGYUD
MA ZHI BAR BYED PA'I
SEMS BYUNG SEMS PA
A state of mind which ruins
the peace of mind of
the person who has it.
A state of mind which ruins
the peace of mind of
the person who has it.
Definition of a klesha, negative emotion.
And it's prickly.
That's the point.
It disturbs your peace of
mind because it's prickly.
Jealousy is prickly.
And when you keep jealousy in your heart,
then you can't really be jolly all day.
So you've always got
something bothering you.
Jolly all day is a great spiritual goal.
All right.
Next verse.
,LAS DANG NYON MONGS PA DAG NI,
,LUS RNAMS KYI NI RKYEN DU BSTAN,
,GAL TE LAS DANG NYON MONGS PA,
,DE STONG LUS LA JI LTAR BRJOD,
LAS DANG NYON MONGS PA DAG NI
These two things that
we've been talking about,
karma and negative emotions,
LUS RNAMS KYI NI RKYEN DU BSTAN
they were taught by the Buddha
to be the RKYEN of your LUS.
To be the cause of your mortal coil.
This is a English special
expression, mortal coil.
Yes, the body, the dying body
that you are wearing right now.
It's called mortal coil.
I don't know why coil.
It wraps around you, or something.
Anyway, this clothing called your body,
which will be dropped,
it's caused by two factors,
karma and negative emotions.
GAL TE LAS DANG NYON MONGS PA
DE STONG
If the karma and negative emotions
which creates your body are STONG,
"empty", then LUS LA JI LTAR BRJOD
Then what? Duh.
What do you think the body will be?
JI LTAR BRJOD
What did you think the body?
Did you think it's not going to be empty?
If the body is made by
two super-empty things,
then the body's also super-empty.
That's Nagarjuna.
I have a picture of a skyscraper
made with bubbles.
It was midnight, I was getting silly.
I don't quite remember why.
I mean...
if the things that are
the foundations of an entity are impure,
then the entity is
going to be impure also.
And it probably won't stand very well.
Next one.
In these next three verses,
the other guy gets to come back
and insist that he's right.
Here we go.
Karma must exist from its own side.
All right.
And now, specifically,
the other guy's going
to talk about the person
who commits the karma.
He wants to prove,
he's done trying to prove that
the karma has its own nature.
He wants to prove that
the person who commits
the karma has their own nature.
He kind of gave up on, okay Nargarjuna,
suppose the karma doesn't
have its own nature.
And therefore, the body,
it's not true that the body
doesn't have its own nature
because the thing that made the body
didn't have its own nature.
Let's give up on that.
Let's just talk about the
guy who committed the karma:
good karma or bad karma.
Do they have a nature of their own?
Well, listen, Nagarjuna,
,MA RIG BSGRIBS PA'I SKYE BO GANG,
You got a person, SKYE BO,
who's blinded, BSGRIBS PA,
by MA RIG PA.
Misunderstanding.
So the other guy's
showing he's a Buddhist.
Maybe he's Abhidharma or something.
Look, come on, let's talk
about normal sansara.
You got a person who has blinded by,
they don't understand anything.
Let's go back to the verse.
,SRED LDAN DE MI ZA BA PO,
That person who has SRED PA,
meaning desire.
It doesn't mean you like sex.
It means you attach to thinking things
come from their own side.
Which means you can
also get anger from it,
with your husband, for example.
If you think he's coming
from his own side.
And then comes this beautiful word,
ZA BA PO
ZA BA means to eat dinner.
What's a ZA BA PO?
Yeah.
But what's the dinner?
[someone speaking indistinctly]
We're talking about someone
who commits a karma.
- [Student] It's a result of that.
- What? Why refer to the person who
commits a karma as the eater?
Why should we call the consumer?
The eater.
[someone speaking indistinctly]
Yeah, then he's going to eat the result.
Perfect.
The person who commits the karma
will become the consumer of
the result of that karma.
You're going to have, what do you call it?
You eat your cake, or...
- [Student] Have your
cake and eat it, too.
- No, there's another one.
You're going to have to
eat the meal you cooked.
- [Student] Make your bed and lie in it.
- Yeah, you made your bed and now
you're going to have to lie in it.
You hurt somebody,
two weeks later you're
going to be the ZA BA PO.
You're going to eat that karma,
it's going to come back to you.
$100: can you guess what
the discussion is here?
I'll say it again.
You did a karma, the karma stayed as..
"don't lose it".
And then it came back to you.
What's the question going to be here?
What's the Nagarjuna's
question he would bring up, Tim?
- [Tim] Person would have to be a....
- Yes, perfect, perfect.
Hundred dollars for that young man.
We're interested in
what happened to the guy
who made the karma.
And what's his relation to the...?
Eater.
Yes, to the consumer.
He makes the pie,
two weeks later another guy eats the pie.
What's their relationship?
Is he still that guy?
And that doesn't make sense.
Right?
Good answer.
You're already thinking like Nagarjuna.
,SRED LDAN DE MI ZA BA PO,
,DE YANG BYED LAS GZHAN MIN ZHING,
Are they someone different from the
BYED?
Here BYED means 'doer'.
It doesn't mean to do.
BYED PA PO
Unfortunately we're in poetry,
and we got to cut the words short.
Then, Nagarjuna says,
BYED PA PO LAS GZHAN MIN
The guy who eats the result of the action
two weeks later he is not GZHAN.
Yeah, he's not a different
guy, he's the same guy.
What?
[laughing]
He's the same guy,
,DE NYID DE YANG MA YIN NO,
By the way, this is the other guy talking.
I'm sorry, I should of said that.
It's the same guy who eats the karma,
who did the karma two weeks ago.
That's the same guy.
But in another way,
DE NYID DE YANG MA YIN
When you think about it,
it's not really the same guy, either.
So it seems like the
debater, the other debater?
He's waffling.
He says, "Come on, it's the same guy."
And he says, "But in a way,
he's not the same guy, is he?"
So he's waffling.
Then here is our reply.
Nagarjuna comes to the rescue.
,GANG GI PHYIR NA LAS 'DI NI,
,RKYEN LAS BYUNG BA MA YIN ZHING,
If karma existed from its own side,
it could never come from a cause.
that would be its identity.
And it could not be
triggered by some action.
,RKYEN MIN LAS BYUNG YOD MIN PA,
If you had a karma that happened
without anybody doing anything,
well that would be a non-existent karma.
,DE PHYIR BYED PA PO YANG MED,
And therefore, since there was no karma,
which was done by anything,
there's nobody who did it.
So why you worried about
whether he's the same
as the other later guy?
Because there is no guy who did it.
Because he's not possible,
because usually karma
comes from its own side.
Nagarjuna is really kicking his ass.
I'll say it again.
Okay, yes, karma comes from its own side,
and the eater comes from his own side.
Why are you worried about it?
If karma comes from its own side,
then the eater comes from its own side,
then the karma comes from its own side.
The karma comes from its own side,
doesn't have to have a cause.
So nothing's going to happen.
No one's going to do anything.
Why you worried about
the guy who comes later,
if the guy who comes
earlier wasn't there anyway?
Got it?
,GAL TE LAS DANG BYED MED NA,
If there's no action done by nobody,
Got it?
If there's no action done by,
if no action is done by nobody,
,LAS SKYES 'BRAS BU GA LA YOD,
Then how the [mimes expletive]
are you going to have a karmic result?
If there's no action done,
if a non-action is done by a non-body,
then what the hell is the result?
GA LA YOD means what the hell.
It's going to be a non-result.
If a non-action is done by a non-body,
then the non-body's non-action
is going to have a none-result.
Got it?
,CI STE 'BRAS BU YOD MIN NA,
And if there's no result,
why are you so worried about the ZA BA PO?
Yeah. Why are you worried about the guy
who's going to eat the result of the karma
if there's no karma to eat.
Got it?
According to you.
It's getting hot in here.
All right.
I want to have, look at this next picture.
Now, this is amazing.
This is what I want the
Peachtree Cafe to look like.
Whether it will ever
happen, only God knows.
But anyway,
the distinctive feature of this picture is
how many ZA BA POs in this picture?
Nobody.
There's nobody here eating.
If a non-existent karma can be
done by a non-existent guy,
why the hell are you
worried about the eater?
There is no eater.
And I showed you a picture with no eater.
I hope there will be eaters,
but this one has no eaters.
All right, next verse.
Three long, oh my gosh, three verses.
The other guy says,
"If you say karma has no identity at all,
"you are SKUR BA 'DEBS PA-ed,
the Buddhist teaching.
SKUR 'DEBS and SGRO 'DOGS,
we had it yesterday,
somebody won some money.
You are saying something which
does exist doesn't exist.
So the guy comes back.
If there's no eater and
there's nothing to eat,
and nobody made their food to eat,
you are goddamn not
following Buddhist teaching.
You are disrespecting Buddha.
Who's that? The other guy.
Now here's our... here we go.
JI LTAR STON PAS SPRUL
Here's our answer,
and it's the last part of this,
this is the end of the
classes, the end of the course.
Except we will have a
review in the next class.
There will be another class.
But, here's the ultimate answer
from the whole 15 classes.
Here's the ultimate
answer to the accusation
that we are disrespecting the Buddha
because we say nobody eats the karma.
Got it?
Then we say, calm down, calm down.
JI LTAR STON PAS SPRUL PA NI
Listen, can the Buddha emanate or not?
- [Student] Yes.
- Yeah.
By the way, it's two classical emanations:
living and non-living.
What's that mean?
I mean, Buddha can emanate as a fish,
or as a bridge.
The famous example is a bridge,
or a tree,
or the ocean waves to teach you
when you're sitting at
the beach next week.
So can the Buddha
show emanations
that are kind of, how do you say?
They're almost unreal in a way.
Is that tree real?
When the Buddha emanates as a tree,
is it a real tree?
If you climb the tree,
what are you really climbing?
You're climbing Lord Buddha, okay?
- Can Buddha emanate as a tree?
- Yeah, yeah, yeah, we all read
that Buddha can emanate as a tree.
- So when you climb that tree,
you're really climbing up
the Buddha's nose and stuff.
- No, no, no, no, no.
It's just kind of an illusion.
The real Buddha is up in the
heaven, LONGS SPRUL, Tushita heaven.
He's just emanating a tree.
I'm not like disrespecting the Buddha
when I climb on a tree
that the Buddha's emanating
because that's not really the Buddha,
it's just an emanation of the Buddha.
And then, the Nagarjuna says,
"Okay, I'm cool with that".
JI LTAR STON PAS SPRUL PA NI
Now I have a question for you.
Could the tree put forth an emanation?
Could Buddha, as a tree,
could Buddha emanated as a tree
emanate as an apple on the tree?
- [Student] Sure, yes.
- 10 minutes later, 10 minutes later.
- Huh?
Come on, listen,
Listen, Buddha's emanating as
an apple tree in your backyard.
I know.
Would he or would he not have the power
from that emanated tree
to emanate an apple?
- [Student] Yes.
- Of course, yes.
That's what he's talking about here.
And could he emanate a worm
sitting on the apple
on the tree that he emanated.
- [Student] Yes.
- Could the emanation have an emanation,
and that emanation has another emanation?
- [Student] Yes.
- Yes, good.
You're comfortable with that.
,SLAR YANG GZHAN NI SPRUL PA LTAR,
SLAR YANG GZHAN NI means
he sends out a third emanation.
Could the emanated tree emanate an apple?
Yes.
Could the emanated tree emanate an apple,
emanate a worm?
Yes.
So what do you got the problem with karma?
What's your problem?
It's the same.
You do something. It creates a seed.
And that creates a result.
You are emanating a seed,
and then the seed emanates a result,
and the result kicks you in the ass.
What's your problem?
Why do you have a problem with that?
He says, "Well, it's kind of similar."
Is it real?
That's the Nargarjuna. Is it real?
Does it have to be real?
Then his own answer is,
,NYON MONGS LAS DANG LUS RNAMS DANG,
,BYED PA PO DANG 'BRAS BU DAG,
When you talk about karma
and mental afflictions
creating a body,
when you talk about an action
creating a karmic result,
it's all like the city of the Gandharvas.
What's a city of the Gandharvas?
The city,
like, not Mexico City,
Gandharva Mexico City.
What's it mean? What's it mean?
There's two kinds of gandharvas.
- [Student] Celestial musicians.
- One is the celestial
musicians who are cool guys.
But the other is DRI ZA
Gandha means sсent.
- Yeah, smell eater, ghost, preta.
Pretas are also called gandharvas.
The city of the pretas...
If you're a preta, and you
see a city on the horizon,
and it's got fountains and apple trees,
and all that kind of stuff,.
And then you run towards it,
and then suddenly it disappears.
It's like a SMIG RGYU RMI LAM.
Last two words of this beautiful chapter.
The last two words of
this beautiful chapter.
It's like an illusion.
It's like a RMI LAM.
It's like a dream.
Yes, the karmic results that
you are experiencing are like a dream.
The sustaining of that karmic energy
until the result comes back
to you is like a dream.
The action in the first
place was like a dream.
It's like an apple tree
emanated by the Buddha,
a fake apple tree giving fake fruits,
and fake worms sitting on
the fruit. It's the same.
It's the same. It's an illusion.
Why is it an illusion?
It looks like it's
coming from its own side,
but it's not. It's coming from you.
Got it?
Can you eat the apple?
- [Student] Yes.
- Yes, you can.
You can eat the Buddha's finger,
whatever it was that he
was emanating as the apple.
All right, you can eat it.
You can experience karmic results.
Even though the whole process
is not what you thought.
Because the Buddha can emanate.
Now, how deep you go
in that comparison is up to you.
If you are tantric practitioner,
it's an interesting question.
All the things that ever happened to you,
from all the karma you ever did,
how are you supposed to think about it?
That's a another question.
For you Medicine Buddha practitioners.
Let's stop there, we got
one more class to go.
We're going to review
this whole course. Yay!